Guide to the D. Michael Fisher Papers, 1969-2004 AIS.2007.07
ULS Archives & Special Collections
D. Michael Fisher Papers
1969-2004
1996-2002
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Fisher, D. Michael
AIS.2007.07
16.17 Linear Feet (17 boxes)
The D. Michael Fisher Papers document the political career and senatorial, attorney general, and gubernatorial campaigns of Mike Fisher. The material in this collection includes information related to Pennsylvania political campaigns, such as consultant surveys, correspondence, financial information, issue files, news clippings, polling studies, press releases, research files, videos of commercials and debates.
Previous Citation
D. Michael Fisher Papers, 1969-2004, AIS.2007.07, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Arrangement
This collection is divided into nine series:
Series I. Pennsylvania State Senate
Series II. 1996 Attorney General Campaign
Series III. Attorney General's Office Insurance Fraud Investigation Report
Series IV. 2000 Attorney General Campaign
Series V. 2002 Gubernatorial Campaign
Series VI. Post-2002 File
Series VII. Memorabilia
Series VIII. Photographs
Series IX. Audio-Visual Material
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of D. Michael Fisher on October 4, 2007.
Scope and Content Notes
The D. Michael Fisher Papers comprises material created throughout Mike Fisher's political career including his tenure as Pennsylvania senator, attorney general, and governor. The materials are primarily focused on Fisher's campaigns though a small amount of information on his time in various political offices exists. There are no materials related to Fisher's time as a Representative and only one item from his judicial career.
Biography
Dennis Michael 'Mike' Fisher is a Federal Judge on the United States Court of Appeals for the Third Circuit. He was nominated by President George W. Bush on May 1, 2003 and confirmed by the Senate later that year. Fisher was born 1944 in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania to C. Francis and Dolores Darby Fisher. He is married to Carol Hudak Fisher and has two children, Michelle Lynn and Brett Michael. Mike Fisher studied at Georgetown University where he earned a bachelor's degree in 1966 and his law degree in 1969.
In 1969 Fisher was a law clerk in a private practice before becoming the Assistant District Attorney for the Allegheny County District Attorney's Office in 1970. In 1974 he successfully ran for Pennsylvania House of Representatives where he served until 1980. From 1980-1996 he was a member of the Pennsylvania Senate. In 1994 he made an unsuccessful bid for Governor, but lost the GOP nomination to Tom Ridge. In 1996 he was elected Attorney General of Pennsylvania, where he served two terms (1996-2003). In 2002 he gained the Republican nomination for Pennsylvania Governor running against Democratic candidate Ed Rendell. Though Fisher's bid for governor was ultimately unsuccessful he was nominated by President Bush to the U.S. Court of Appeals for the Third Circuit in 2003.
During his tenure as attorney general, Fisher focused heavily on combating illegal drugs. His office made over 6,000 drug related arrests during Fisher's time in office. In 1999 Mike Fisher and eight other attorney generals negotiated a $206 billion settlement with the tobacco industry of which Pennsylvania received $11.3 billion.
Pennsylvania -- Politics and government -- 1951-; Political campaigns -- Pennsylvania; Politics; Government; Fisher, D. Michael; Scaringi, Marc A.; Nutt, Brian; Gates, Kent; Pennsylvania. Attorney General's Office -- Elections, 2000; Pennsylvania. Attorney General's Office -- Elections, 1996; Pennsylvania. Governor -- Elections, 2002; Pennsylvania. General Assembly. Senate -- Elections, 1994
- Pennsylvania State Senate, 1992-1995; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  The Pennsylvania State Senate series is comprised of a small amount of materials related to Fisher's time as a senator (1980-1996). It includes information on his trip to the Republican National Convention in 1992; financial information, press releases, and news articles for his 1994 re-election campaign; and newspaper clippings related to his accomplishments as a Pennsylvania senator.
  - 1992 Republican National Convention, 1.
    The 1992 Republican Nation Convention sub-series is comprised of materials from Mike Fisher's time as an RNC delegate for Bush/Quayle in 1992. It includes badges, a commemorative passport, Fisher's golf scorecard, and notes on Bill Clinton.
    - Republican Nation Convention delegate materials, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1994 Fisher for Senator Campaign, 1993-1994; 2.
    Materials in the 1994 Fisher for Senator Campaign sub-series include campaign financial reports, media reports and clippings, and information of the Ridge/Schweiker gubernatorial campaign. There is also a brochure for the failed 1986 Scranton/Fisher gubernatorial campaign - it is the only item in this collection related to Fisher's bid for leiutenant governor.
    Fisher's campaign was managed by James C. Roddey -- former Port Authority Board Chairman, and then current Managing General Partner of Allegheny Media, later to become Pennsylvania's first County Executive -- who served as campaign chairman, and Gregory A. Harbaugh -- Allegheny Co. fundraiser for Bush presidential campaign and senior partner in Houston Harbaugh law firm -- who was campaign treasurer.
    - Brochure from 1986 Bill Scranton for Governor, Mike Fisher for Lt. Governor campaign (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Finances -- Campaign expense reports, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Finances -- Fisher 94 Committee checkbooks, 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Finances -- Contributor correspondence, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Finances -- Event expenses, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - News releases and articles, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      1 b/w headshot print of Fisher
    - Press releases, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Tom Ridge for Governor Committee finances, November 22, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Tom Ridge for Governor information book and Ridge/Schweiker campaign brochure (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Senate, 1995; 3.
    The Senate 1995 sub-series is comprised entirely of clippings from newspapers regarding the actions of Senator Fisher. These were likely assembled as material to boost Fisher's image in his 1996 bid for Attorney General.
    - News clips regarding Senator Fisher, January-July 1995 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- 1996 Attorney General Campaign, 1972-1996; 1995-1996; II.
  The 1996 Attorney General Campaign documents the Fisher campaign and includes campaign analysis research, correspondence, event and fundraising information, newspaper clippings, and press materials. During the 1996 campaign season, Mike Fisher ran against Democratic candidate, Joseph Kohn; Fisher was successfully elected as the Attorney General of Pennsylvania.
  The bulk of the in this series date from 1995-1996; unless otherwise noted, all files fall within this range. The most common date note is for specific dates, though occasionally materials fall well outside this range; see in particular the Opposition Research sub-series on Democratic attorney general nominee, Joseph C. Kohn.
  - Clippings of Newspapers and Other Sources for Attorney General Candidates, 1995-1996; 1.
    This sub-series is comprised of articles and news clippings related to Fisher and his opponents for Attorney General. The two largest folders are Fisher's and Mike Marino, the other Republican candidate.
    - Tom Corbet news clips (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Mike Fisher clips (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Joe Kohn clips (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Mike Marino clips and brochures (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1995-1996; 2.
    The Correspondence sub-series includes letters, memos, and other correspondence primarily from supporters, staff, constituents, and Republican or other interest groups. It also includes a letter from Mike Marino to Allegheny County Republican Chairman, Robert W. Cramer.
    - Ads for booklets (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Area Agency on Aging, March 15, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - African American Coalition, December 1, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Announcements (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - College Republicans of Pennsylvania (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - County Chairs and State Committee letter draft, April 20, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Outgoing correspondence (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Coordinator mailings (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Letters to editor campaign (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Memoranda (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - National Rifle Association (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Opponents' correspondence -- contains only Mike Marino letter, April 15, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Pennsylvania Council of Republican Women (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Regret letters (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - County Files, 1995-1996; 3.
    The County Files sub-series are comprised of materials related to Republican supporters in various Pennsylvania counties. They include correspondence with supporters and County Coordinators, Steering Committee and other membership lists, and event information and schedules
    - Fisher campaign County Coordinator lists (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Memos to/from County Coordinators (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Adams County (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Bedford County (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Berks County (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Blair County (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Bradford County (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Bucks County (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Cameron County (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Chester County (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Clarion County (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Clearfield County (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Columbia County (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Crawford County (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Cumberland County (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Clinton County (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Dauphin County (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Delaware County (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Elk County (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Erie County (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Forest County (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Franklin County (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Fulton County (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Huntingdon County (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Jefferson County (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Juniata County (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Lackawanna County (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Lancaster County (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Lebanon County (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Lehigh County (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Luzerne County (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Lycoming County (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - McKean County (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Mercer County (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Mifflin County (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Montour County (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Montgomery County (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Northampton County (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Northumberland County (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Perry County (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Philadelphia (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Pike County (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Potter County (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Schuylkill County (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Sullivan County (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Snyder County (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Susquehanna County (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Tioga County (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Union County (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Venango County (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Warren County (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Wayne County (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Wyoming County (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - York County (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Finances, 1996-1997; 4.
    The Finances sub-series includes information on Fisher's campaign's fiscal status including expenses, contributions, and disbursements. It also includes a small amount of material on the campaign's financial plans and the Finance Committee generally.
    - Campaign Expense Reports, May-October 1996 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Campaign Expense Reports, October-November 1996 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Check registers (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Contribution reports, June 1996 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Contribution reports, July 1996 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Contribution reports, August 1996 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Contribution reports, September 1996 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Contribution reports, October 1996 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Campaign correspondence (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Disbursement report for Jon, January 1997 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Finance Committee structure (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Finance Plan, June 27, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Fundraising -- Eastern (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Statement of Cash Receipts and Disbursements (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Opposition Research on Joseph Kohn, 1983-1996; 5.
    The Opposition Research on Joseph Kohn sub-series compiles research assembled by the Fisher campaign on 1992 and 1996 Democratic attorney general nominee, Joseph Kohn. This sub-series includes background investigations into Kohn's personal life as well as his legal and political career. Much of the material includes annotations or descriptions as to its utility for Fisher's campaign strategy.
    - Background information on Kohn's legal career, August 1996 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Biographical, legal, and positional research on Joe Kohn (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Kohn case research -- AIDS case, Doe v. Kohn et al, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Kohn case research -- Amino Acid Lysine antitrust litigation (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Kohn case research -- Air transportation antitrust suit, 1990-1994 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Kohn case research -- Carpet cases, 1993-1995 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Kohn case research -- Centennial School District v. Independence Blue Cross, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Kohn case research -- Cumberland Farms, Inc., et al. v. Browning-Ferris Industries, Inc., 1988 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Kohn case research -- The Department of Stripper Well exemption litigation, 1987-1996 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Kohn case research -- Scott Doe dockets (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Kohn case research -- General Motors pickup truck fuel tank products liability litigation, 1993-1996 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Kohn case research -- J/H Real Estate, Inc. v. Leonard Abramson, et al. (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Kohn case research -- Lutheran church RICO case, 1992-1996 (Box 3, Folder 9-10)
    - Kohn case research -- Mishel et al. v. Nutri/System, Inc., et al., 1984 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Kohn case research -- "No" files, 1983-1996 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Kohn case research -- Paoli Railroad Yard PCB litigation (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Kohn case research -- Parkway Garage, Inc. v. The City of Philadelphia, 1992-1996 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Kohn general research -- Gun control (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Kohn general research -- John Wasilchick's opposition research proposal and report (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Kohn general research -- Plagiarism, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Kohn general research -- RICO knowledge, 1988-1996 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Press releases from Fisher campaign regarding Joseph Kohn (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Polling Research, 1996; 6.
    The Polling Research sub-series contains statistical research gathered from surveys of voters leading up to Fisher's election.
    - Key Findings from a Survey of Voter Attitudes in the State of Pennsylvania, May 14-15, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 20-21)
    - Key Findings from a Survey of Voter Attitudes in the State of Pennsylvania, May 18, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Poll cards (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Press Releases, 1995-1996; 7.
    The Press Releases sub-series consists of materials generated by the Fisher for Attorney General campaign to highlight Fisher's qualification as well as to introduce him and his positions.
    - Biographical and background information about Mike Fisher (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Positions taken by Fisher during campaign (Box 3, Folder 25)
      Includes Fisher's positions on: crime, environment, firearms, senior citizens, tobacco, and women's issues.
    - Press releases, November 1995-September 1996 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Press releases, September-November 1996 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Subject Files, 1972-1996; 8.
    The Subject Files sub-series is comprised of materials of which are too small to comprise their own groupings. As such it consists a range of material including campaign stickers, balloons, brochures, and other ephemera; debates; events and agendas for Fisher; general election results; instructional guides to campaign staffers; non-Attorney General candidate information; and Republican State Committee information.
    - Campaign ephemera and other materials (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Election results (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Endorsements (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Fisher campaign agreements (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Fisher tailgate party for PSU/Iowa game, October 1996 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Joseph Kohn and D. Michael Fisher Bar Association debate transcript, October 17, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - 1995 and 1996 newspaper directories (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Phone bank instructions and scripts (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Prime sponsor Bills of Fisher as a Senator and Representative, 1972-1996 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Priority precincts (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Questionnaires (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Reports on campaign activities (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Representative meeting agendas (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Republican State Committee delegates committed to Fisher (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Republican State Committee political brochures, 1994-1996 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Schedules (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Sheriffs' party affiliations of counties in Pennsylvania (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Bob Shuster for Congress campaign materials (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Trips and Travels During Campaign, 9.
    The Trips and Travels sub-series documents Fisher's travels around Pennsylvania during the 1996 Attorney General Campaign.
    - Proposed trips (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Statewide tour, October-November 1996 (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Attorney General's Office Insurance Fraud Investigation Report, April 1997; III.
  The Attorney General's Office Insurance Fraud Investigation Report series comprises the only extant materials of Fisher's tenure as attorney general outside of campaign purposes. The three files of this series are taken from an April 1997 report and press release from the Office of Attorney General -- Criminal Law Division -- Bureau of Criminal Investigations -- Insurance Fraud Section. The report details twenty-six arrests broken into sections arranged by suspect's last name.
  - Insurance fraud arrest report -- Butela-Fritz, April 1997 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Insurance fraud arrest report -- Giliano-Lyle, April 1997 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Insurance fraud arrest report -- Miller-Woodring, April 1997 (Box 4, Folder 23)
- 2000 Attorney General Campaign, 1996-2000; 1999-2000; IV.
  The 2000 Attorney General Campaign series consists of materials for Mike Fisher's attention as the Attorney General candidate. It consists of campaign promotional materials, finance information, and campaign analysis reports.
  - Campaign and promotional materials, 1999-2000 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Finances -- Advertising and polling costs notebook, 1996-2000 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    Sections: Schedule (empty); Fundraising; Account Balance (empty); and TV Buy.
  - Finances -- Advertising and polling costs notebook (Box 4, Folder 26)
    Sections: Results; Mail/Phones; Print ads; and Radio.
  - Finances -- Advertising and polling costs notebook (Box 4, Folder 27)
    Sections: Tracking; and Editorials
  - Finances -- Daily contribution reports, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Reports -- Brabender Cox -- Analysis of Fisher Print Media Coverage, September 29, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Reports -- Tarrance Group -- Key Findings from a Statewide Survey of Voter Attitudes in Pennsylvania, February 10, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 30)
- 2002 Gubernatorial Campaign, 1975-2002; V.
  The materials in the 2002 Governor Campaign series comprise materials related to Fisher's 2002 gubernatorial campaign. Fisher was nominated as the Republican candidate, Jane Earll ran as Lieutenant Governor. Fisher ran against Ed Rendell, the Democratic nominee, in the primary election. Fisher's other opponents in the race included Bob Casey, Jr. and Barbara Hafer. Materials in this series include campaign memorabilia, correspondence, campaign finance information, press releases, research on campaign issues, news briefing packets, files of Fisher's opponents, and polling/survey research.
  - Campaign Materials, 2002; 1.
    The Campaign Materials sub-series includes campaign advertisements, Fisher campaign staff information, and a file of organizations endorsing Fisher for Attorney General.
    - Campaign ads (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Campaign staff contact information (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Endorsements (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 2002; 2.
    The Correspondence sub-series is comprised of issue related correspondence from various constituents and organizations in Pennsylvania. Several pieces of correspondence relate to organizations seeking to endorse a candidate based on their political views and positions.
    - Act 9 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Animal rights (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - County committees (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Gambling (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - General info (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Education (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Gun control (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Liquor (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Mental retardation (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Personal care (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Prison (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Pro-life (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Property taxes (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Teacher pension (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Volunteers (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Wants something (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Direct Mail Files, 2002; 3.
    The Direct Mail Files sub-series documents the creation of form letters for events and individuals related to the Fisher campaign.
    - George W. Bush (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Carol Fisher (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - D. Michael Fisher (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Harrisburg Rally (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Pennsylvania auto association (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Pennsylvania food merchants (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Ridge House, Republican State Committee (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - Santorum (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - Schweiker (Box 5, Folder 28)
      - Donor Briefings, 2002; 4.
        The Donor Briefings sub-series consists of information generated by Fisher's staff concerning important donors to the Fisher campaign.
        - Donor briefings (Box 5, Folder 29-30)
  - Finances, 1999-2002; 5.
    The Finances sub-series is comprised of financial information of Fisher's gubernatorial campaign. It is divided into three sections: Fundraising Events, Major Donor Files, and Subject Files. The Fundraising Events includes event information, briefing memos to Mike Fisher, donation spreadsheets, and correspondence. The Major Donor Files are arranged alphabetically Abrams to Zimmerman; a given file will contain a briefing memorandum for Fisher, copies of the donation checks, and/or thank you notes. The Subject Files contains additional financial information that would not fit into other sections; these include campaign finance reports, a sampled selection of mail-in contributions, a list of pro-life donors, and Fisher's staff's salary information.
    Check copies, invoices, and yes/no attendance cards have all been removed from this series.
    Mike Fisher thank you notes have been sampled throughout. Notes with unique messages have been retained.
    - Fundraising Events, January 12-May 30, 2002
      - Jeb Bush timeline in Philadelphia, January 2, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 31)
      - Terpeluk dinner meeting, January 8, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 32)
      - Delaware County dinner, January 17, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 33)
      - Lunch with George Glatfelter II and Peter Yaffee, January 17, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 34)
      - UPS dinner, January 22, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 35)
      - Hershey Entertainment and Resorts Company PAC, January 30, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 36)
      - Republican State Committee dinner, February 8, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 37)
      - Highmark Health System's PAC, February 19, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 38)